Preliminary Guide to the Collection of Drawing and Painting on Paper
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Drawing and Painting on Paper
1875-1899
AOB 73
Yale University Arts Library
0.75
(3 boxes + 1 oversize folder)
This collection contains examples of drawings and paintings on paper. Many of these pieces were intended for use or used as illustrations in published works. The majority of the collection is late 19th century. There are two paintings on un-stretched canvas.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Collection of Drawing and Painting on Paper was housed in the former Arts of the Book Collection until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
Curatorial permission required before use.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains examples of drawings and paintings on paper. Many of these pieces were intended for use or used as illustrations in published works. The majority of the collection is late 19th century. There are two paintings on unstretched canvas.
Arrangement
Organized into six series: I. Figurative. II. Landscape/Architecture. III. Maps. IV. Nature. V. Ornamentation. VI. Miscellaneous.
Illustration of books; Painting -- 19th century; Drawing -- 19th century; Paintings (visual works); Drawings (visual works)
- Figurative, Series I
  Scope and Contents
  This series includes illustrations, cartoons, and two oil paintings. Subjects include pastoral, domestic, humorous, sporting, political (notably two political cartoons on feminism), and several portraits. Of particular note are an original print from 1597 (Folder 4) and an erotic Western scene (Folder 5).
  - Figurative illustrations, 1911 undated; 10 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Figurative illustrations, undated; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Figurative illustrations, 1958-[1967] undated; 6 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Figurative illustrations, 1597 1817-1875 undated; 13 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Figurative illustrations, undated; 7 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Figurative illustrations, [1904] undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Figurative illustrations, undated; 5 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Figurative illustrations, undated; 26 items (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Konigan's Irish Fairies, 1897; 1 (Folder 1)
  - Athletic theme, 1904 undated; 6 (Folder 1)
  - Town hall type scene, signed "A. Castaigne", undated; 1 (Folder 1)
- Landscape/Architecture, Series II
  This series includes mostly single matted outdoor scenes, some containing small figures. Several pieces are multi-paned matted scenes.
  - Landscape/Architecture illustrations, undated; 10 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Landscape/Architecture illustrations, undated; 5 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Landscape/Architecture illustrations, undated; 12 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Landscape/Architecture illustrations, undated; 6 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Landscape/Architecture illustrations, undated; 2 (Folder 1)
- Maps, Series III
  - Route of the "Flotsam", undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Bartlesville, Oklahoma, 1917; 1 (Folder 1)
- Nature, Series IV
  This series includes hand-painted illustrations of birds, fish, and other animals. Of particular note is a still life of fish, shells, and flowers.
  - Nature illustrations, 1834-1895 undated; 21 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- Ornamentation, Series V
  This series includes frontispiece borders, patterns, and an illuminated text.
  - Ornamentation illustrations, undated; 7 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous, Series VI
  - 2 collages, 1 illustration of a printing press, undated 1873; 3 (Box 3, Folder 16)